<?xml version="1.0"?>
<speakers>
	<version>1.0</version>
	<speaker>
		<name>Sanchir Tserendorj</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Ms. Sanchir is an artist and expert in Mongolian art and cultural studies. As Director of the Organization for the Study of diaspora Mongols, she initiated the making of documentary episodes about diaspora Mongols, working on research, photography, and the film script.
		
In 2004, Ms. Sanchir directed 30 research and documentary video expeditions to Islamic countries, closed countries in the Middle East about diaspora Mongolian groups. In 2009-2010, Ms. Sanchir was the leader of TASAM-12 documentary series, research and video expedition team.
		
In 2010 Ms. Sanchir was the project leader for Mongols with a Royal History, a project recounting the story of diaspora Mongols who had been posted to secure the conquered land and their distinct ethnic uniqueness, traditions, and clothing which they have preserved, and the tangible cultural heritage Mongols built during the 100 years of their reign in Middle Eastern countries.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/sanchir-tserendorj.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>
	<speaker>
		<name>Didi Kalika</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>In 1993 Didi Kalika, an Australian yoga teacher living in UB was moved by the plight of the children living on the streets and founded the Lotus Children's Centre. She started simply by giving food and basic medical care, and soon realized that serious change was necessary to make real impact. With the help of friends, Didi arranged a yard in the ger district of Yarmag 15 km out of UB. The move to Yarmag was necessary to give children space away from their lives on the streets of UB. In 1995, the Lotus Children's Centre was registered as an official Mongolian charity. Towards the end of the 90's, the children Lotus served moved from mainly street kids to abandoned babies. Due to harsh economic conditions, some Mongolian families found it hard to keep their newborn babies. Mongolian authorities asked Lotus to care for babies that were found under stairwells or in rubbish bins, often in the depth of winter. The Lotus Centre started a Kindergarten on the Yarmag property in 1997. It was around this time that their summer camp started, sending kids to the National Park in Terelj for their summer holidays to play and swim.
		
Didi was awarded Mongolian mother of the year award in 2001. She was also made a Paul Harris fellow by the Rotary Club of Canberra Sunshine.

Due to the lack of necessary paperwork for Lotus children to start at government schools, in 2004, Lotus converted an old general goods store in Yarmag into a primary school. The kindergarten was moved into the same building. This was necessary to guarantee that all Lotus children would have an education up to the 5th grade. Around this time the situation of children in Mongolia gradually improved, with less babies coming to the center. The Lotus Centre is now home to up to 150 children at any one time. It carries out many children and family support activities aimed at helping family units endure. The Lotus Centre aims to alleviate the poverty cycle and to ultimately provide basic rights to children.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/didi-kalika.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>
	<speaker>
		<name>Ganhuyag Chuluun Hutagt</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Ganhuyag started his career at the Mongolian Stock Exchange as a floor supervisor in 1991 and moved on to become engaged in the family trading business a year later. He joined the Central Bank’s Supervision Division after graduating from the Budapest University of Economic Sciences in 1997. He was hired by UNDP’s MicroStart Pilot Project in 1998, initially as a Finance Manager and then Operations Manager before becoming the Executive Director of Mongolia’s first non-bank financial company X.A.C. (Golden Fund for Development). In 1999. X.A.C. subsequently merged with USAID funded Goviin Ekhlel (GobiStart) LLC to form XacBank. He held the position of the CEO of XacBank from the founding until 2009.
		
In June 2007, he was elected to the Board of the Microfinance Center for Central Asia and Eastern Europe and the New Independent States (MFC). He has been serving as the Honorary Consul of the Republic of Hungary in Mongolia since 2006 and as the President of the Mongolian Students’ Union since January 2010. The World Economic Forum named him a Young Global Leader in 2009.

Before being appointed as the Vice Minister of Finance of Mongolia in December 2010, he worked as the CEO of TenGer Financial Group and the economic policy advisor to the Prime Minister of Mongolia.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/ganhuyag-chuluun.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
</speakers>