<?xml version="1.0"?>
<speakers>
	<version>1.0</version>
	<speaker>
		<name>Jack Weatherford</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>In the 14th century, the North African scholar Ibn Khaldun wrote the first historical work to focus on tribalism as the key to understanding human civilization. In his analysis, civilization faces an eternal dilemma and needs tribal values to survive. In his scholarship, Professor Weatherford tries to follow the tradition of Ibn Khaldun by studying the relationship of tribal people to the larger societies around them and to world history.
 
Professor Weatherford is a cultural anthropologist who has been teaching Anthropology at Macalester since 1983. He graduated from the University of South Carolina in 1967, with a B.A in Political Science followed by a M.A. in Sociology in 1972. He also received a M.A in Anthropology in 1973 and a Ph.D in Anthropology from the University of California, San Diego. He went on to post-doctoral work in the Institute of Policy Sciences at Duke University.
 
Dr. Weatherford has worked with contemporary groups in places such as Bolivia and the Amazon with emphasis on the role of tribal people in world history. The April 2000 issue from the Chronicle of Higher Education gives an overview of some of that work. In recent years, he has concentrated on the Mongols. His book Genghis Khan and the Making of the Modern World was an international best seller published in more than twenty languages. In 2007 President Enkhbayar of Mongolia awarded him the Order of the Polar Star, Mongolia’s highest national award, in recognition of his contribution to Mongolian culture. His most recent work, The Secret History of the Mongol Queens, is the first book written on the daughters of Genghis Khan.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/Jack_Weatherford_Headsho.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>
	<speaker>
		<name>Chris Cartwright</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Chris started his career in Outdoor Education in the English Lake District back in 1983. His career quickly progressed as he gained experience and a vast array of high qualifications in the field of Outdoor Education. Initially tutoring on youth development programmes he gained a valuable insight into the fundamental and profound learning that could be gained from well structured, planned and professionally facilitated events. Later, in 1988 he turned his sights to leading international expeditions, around the world, a month at a time, again focussing on youth development. From 1990 Chris concentrated on Canoe sport and Mountaineering as activities and on Development Training as his chosen vehicle for education. It was on one of these expeditions in 2003 that he first came to visit Mongolia. Since 1988, Chris has lead over 230 expeditions visiting well over 50 countries worldwide. During his first visit to Mongolia Chris was really taken by the fantastic nature, history and traditions of the country. However, in recent times the greater urbanisation has become a burden upon the nomadic population and communities adaptability. Therefore, in 2010 Chris established the Mongolia Institute of Outdoor Learning, as a way of getting young Mongolians back into the countryside on professional Outdoor Learning events, facilitated to international standards.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/Chris_Cartwright.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
	<speaker>
		<name>Oyundary Tsagaan</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>As a Managing Director of Mongolian National Public Television, Oyundary Tsagaan is a well-regarded broadcast journalist in Mongolia. She received a BA Degree in Political Economy in 1993 from the Academy of State and Social Studies. After graduation, she worked at the National Television as a field reporter and a political commentator. Later she worked with National Television’s management team as a Program Director for a year starting from 1997, then with Eagle Television, a Mongolian-American Joint venture, for two years as an Assistant general manager and chief operations officer, and also was the press assistant to a Mongolian Prime Minister in 1998.

She spent 6 years in the U.S.A. between 2002 and 2008, first learning English, and then working at several companies in America including CBS’s Local News Station in San Francisco, to grasp American work standards and then incorporate them into work projects; later in 2006, she went to the University of California, Berkeley, and in 2008, earned a masters degree in journalism. 

She received an Order of Honor for “Best Achievement in Radio and Television” in 2009, an Order of Honor for “Press Freedom” in 2000 from the Union of Mongolian Professional Journalists, and also won the Journalist of the Year Award in 1997 from the Union of Mongolian Professional Journalists. While she was at the Graduate School of Journalism, UC Berkeley, she won the Emmy Scholarship from the National Television Academy, and also Summer Fellowship from the Human Rights Center, UC Berkeley, in 2007.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Монголын ард түмэн Цагааны Оюундарийг МҮОНТ-ийн захирал, телевизийн сэтгүүлч гэдгээр нь сайн танина. Тэрээр 1993 онд Улстөр, Нийгэм Судлалын Академийг улстөрийн эдийн засаг чиглэлээр төгссөн. Сургуулиа төгссөнийхөө дараа тэрээр үндэсний телевизэд сурвалжлагч, улс төрийн тоймчоор ажиллах болсон. Ц.Оюундарь 1997 оноос МҮОНТ-ийн удирдлагын багт Програмын захирлаар нэг жил, Монгол-Америкийн хамтарсан хөрөнгө оруулалттай Eagle телевизэд ерөнхий туслах менежер ба ахлах удирдлагаар 2 жилийн турш ажилласан бөгөөд 1998 оноос Монгол улсын ерөнхий сайдын хэвлэлийн туслахын үүргийг гүйцэтгэж байсан юм.

Тэрээр 2002-2008 оны хооронд АНУ-д ажиллаж амьдарсан. Энэ хугацаандаа тэрээр нэгдүгээрт хэлний мэдлэгээ дээшлүүлж, хоёрдугаарт АНУ-ын ажлын стандартыг сурч судлан өөрийн ажлын төслүүддээ нэгтгэн авч хэрэгжүүлэх зорилготойгоор Сан Франциско хотын CBS орон нутгийн мэдээний станц гэх мэт хэд хэдэн компаниудад ажиллаж байлаа. Мөн тэрээр 2006 онд Бэркли (Berkeley) дэхь Калифорниагийн Их Сургууль (University of California)-д элсэн орж, 2008 онд сэтгүүлч мэргэжлээр магистрын зэрэг хамгаалсан юм.

Ц.Оюундарь Монголын Мэргэжлийн Сэтгүүлчдийн Холбооноос 2009 онд “Радио телевизийн шилдэг амжилт” шагнал, 2000 онд “Хэвлэлийн эрх чөлөө” шагналыг тус тус хүртэж байсан бөгөөд 1997 онд оны шилдэг сэтгүүлчээр шалгарч байв.

Тэрээр Бэркли (Berkeley) дэхь Калифорниагийн Их Сургууль (University of California)-д сэтгүүлч мэргэжлээр суралцаж байх хугацаандаа Үндэсний Телевизийн Академи-аас Эмми тэтгэлэг (Emmy Scholarship), 2007 онд Бэркли (Berkeley) дэхь Хүний Эрхийг Хамгаалах Төвөөс зуны тэтгэлэгийг хүртэж байсан юм. </description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/oyundari.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
	<speaker>
		<name>Benj Binks</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Benj Benks is a documentary filmmaker, photographer and blogger who grew up on a farm in Violet Town, Australia. From volunteering in the Amazon to cycling in Cambodia, Benj’s travels have spurred a lust for discovering cultures, places, people and stories. Over the years he has relayed these adventures through writing, photography and film.
		
		Whilst working on the Trans-Siberian in 2004, he stumbled into a Mongolian nightclub bouncing to hip-hop and since 2007 has been working on Mongolian Bling—a documentary about Mongolia’s youth and modern culture.  Benj was fascinated to see the country’s beautiful ancient traditions juxtaposed against the youth’s love of Western culture. Mongolian Bling explores the relationship Mongolia’s youth has with their country’s traditions, many of which the older genereations fear are dying. Four years of working on the project has given Benj a unique insight into modern Mongolia and Ulaanbaatar’s hip-hop scene. Mongolian Bling is due out in 2012.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Баримтат кино найруулагч, зурагчин, блог нийтлэлч Бэнж нь Австралийн Вайлэт (Violet) хотын фермерийн аж ахуйд төрж өссөн.

Үзэх зурагтгүй өнгөрүүлсэн хүүхэл нас нь түүнийг адал явдалд дурлагч, шинийг нээн илрүүлэх хүсэл тэмүүлэлтэй болоход нь нөлөөлсөн бөгөөд энэ нь яваандаа түүнийг дэлхий ертөнцөөр аялахад нь хөтөлжээ. Бэнж Амазон (Amazon)-оос зохион байгуулсан Камбожруу дугуйгаар аялах сайн дурын хөдөлгөөнд оролцсоноосоо хойш шинэ газраар зочилж, олон янзын соёлтой өөр өөр хүмүүстэй танилцаж, төрөл бүрийн түүх сонсох дуртай болсон юм. Өнгөрсөн хугацаанд тэрээр энэхүү өөрийн үзэж туулсан адал явдлаа бичих, гэрэл зурагт буулгах, кино хийх гэх зэргээр олон нийтэд хүргэж байлаа.

Тэрээр 2004 онд Транс-Сибирь (Trans-Siberian)-д  ажиллаж байхдаа Монголын нэгэн хип хоп шөнийн клубт анх орж байсан бөгөөд 2007 оноос хойш Mongolian Bling-т ажиллаж байна.

Бэнж өнөөгийн залуучуудын хошууран шүтэж буй барууны соёлоос илүүтэйгээр эртний сайхан өв уламжлалтай улс орнуудад сэтгэл зүрх нь ихээр татагддаг байв. Бэнж кино хийх хүсэлдээ хөтлөгдөн 3 жилийн дараа нутагтаа буцаж, Монголын залуучууд болон орчин үеийн соёлын тухай баримтат кино хийхээр ажиллаж эхэлсэн.

Mongolian Bling нь устан үгүй болох вий хэмээн ахмад настнууд эмээдэг тус улсын өв уламжлал өнөөгийн залуучуудын амьдралд хэрхэн холбогддог талаар нээн илрүүлдэг. Бэнж 4 жилийн өмнө төсөл дээр ажиллаж байхдаа орчин үеийн Монголын залуучууд ба Улаанбаатар хотын хип хоп хэмнэлийн далд холбоог олж харсан юм.

Тэрээр Монголд 10 дахь удаагаа ирж байгаа бөгөөд албан ёсны оршин суух эрх авахаар хүлээж байгаа юм.

Mongolian Bling төслийн хугацаа 2012 онд дуусах юм.</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/benj-binks.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
	<speaker>
		<name>Carsten Ruebsaamen</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Dr. Carsten Ruebsaamen is Founder and CEO of BOOKBRIDGE, which is a charity organization striving for worldwide balanced access to education. By providing access to books and quality education, BOOKBRIDGE empowers people with a sustainable basis to help themselves and thereby break the cycle of poverty.

BOOKBRIDGE establishes education centers, trains teachers and supplies schools with books. Throughout the developing world, they partner with local communities and educational institutions to provide access to education and improve the quality of existing educational offerings. Their education centers are designed as social businesses, providing young educators with the possibility of a place to work, nurture their knowledge and pass it on to others.

BOOKBRIDGE began as an idea in 2005, when Carsten and a group of German scouts traveled to Mongolia for the first time. Together with Mongolian scouts, they experienced the vastness of the Mongolian landscape, and the hospitality and friendliness of the Mongolian people. Four years, and many visits between Germany and Mongolia later, BOOKBRIDGE began in Mongolia and has impacted the lives of more than 100,000 people. It is now spreading around the world, with offices in Germany, England, Switzerland, Mongolia and the United States. Dr. Ruebsaamen will be speaking on the inspiration Mongolia provided for BOOKBRIDGE and how it is inspiring people around the world.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/carsten.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>		
	<speaker>
		<name>His Holiness the Dalai Lama</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Although he will be traveling to Europe the week of TEDxUlaanbaatar, the Office of His Holiness the Dalai Lama has informed us that they would like to provide us with a letter which can be read at our event. The Dalai Lama holds a special place in the hearts of millions of people in Mongolia and we feel very honored to have his words as part of TEDxUlaanbaatar.

His Holiness the Fourteenth Dalai Lama, Tenzin Gyatso, is a world-renowned spiritual leader who has been working for world peace for decades. He is seen by many as the spiritual leader of Tibet and the Tibetan Government-in-Exile. He has been given hundreds of awards including the Nobel Peace Prize in 1989 and the United State's Congressional Gold Medal in 2007.</description_en>
		<description_mn>NEEDED</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/DalaiLama(bw).jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
	<speaker>
		<name>Oyungerel Tsedevdamba</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Born and raised in Huvsgul Aimag, Mrs. Oyungerel is widely known in Mongolia as a public speaker, author, and passionate advocate for democracy. Mrs. Oyungerel has earned degrees in economic planning, international business, and is also a graduate of Stanford University majoring in international policy studies.

Having initiated, established, and lead a number of civil society and human rights organizations, Mrs. Oyungerel is an eminent public leader and a compassionate social advocate. She is the President of Local Solutions Foundation, an Ulaanbaatar based NGO. She was the first Executive Director of Liberty Center, a human rights watchdog. From 2004 to 2007, Mrs. Oyungerel made strenuous efforts to help the civil society and its individual members to raise funds to run public activities.

Mrs. Oyungerel has authored and published multiple books, including the historical novel, Green-Eyed Lama, which she co-authored with Jeffrey Falt. The book received a keen response from readership and was awarded the Best Book of 2008 Prize by Internom.

She was awarded the 2003 Fulbright Fellowship, and she is a 2006 Yale World Fellow. For her efforts to consolidate Mongolian democracy, secure human rights and liberties, and establish rule of law, Oyungerel was awarded the Order of Liberty by the Mongolian Democratic Union in 2003.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Хөвсгөл аймагт төрж, өссөн хатагтай Ц.Оюунгэрэлийг Монголын ард түмэн гайхалтай илтгэгч, авьяаслаг зохиолч, ардчиллыг тууштай дэмжигч гэдгээр нь сайн танина. Тэрээр эдийн засгийн төлөвлөлт, олон улсын бизнесийн чиглэлээр эрдмийн зэрэг хамгаалсан төдийгүй Станфордын Их Сургуулийг олон улсын бодлого судлал мэргэжлээр төгссөн. 

Олны танил манлайлагч, нийгмийн зүтгэлтэн тэрээр иргэний нийгэм, хүний эрхийг дэмжих хэд хэдэн байгууллагуудыг санаачлан байгуулж, өөрөө удирдан ажилладаг. Ц.Оюунгэрэл одоогоор Улаанбаатар хотод байрлах “Орон нутгийн шийдлийн сан” (Local Solutions Foundation) ТББ-ын тэргүүнээр ажиллаж байна. Хатагтай Ц.Оюунгэрэл 2004-2007 онд иргэний нийгэм болон түүний гишүүн бүрт олон нийтийн арга хэмжээ зохион байгуулах мөнгөн хөрөнгө босгоход нь туслахаар шаргуу ажиллаж, хүчин чармайлт гаргасан юм.

Тэрээр Жэффри Фолт (Jeffrey Falt)-той хамтран бичсэн “Ногоон нүдэн лам” түүхэн роман зэрэг хэд хэдэн номын зохиолчоор ажиллаж, хэвлэлтэнд гаргасан. “Ногоон нүдэн лам” роман нь уншигчдаас өндөр үнэлгээ авсан бөгөөд “Интерном”-оос 2008 оны Шилдэг номоор шагнагдсан юм.

Ц.Оюунгэрэл 2003 онд Фуллбрайтын тэтгэлэг (Fullbright Fellowship), 2006 онд Еэил Их Сургуулийн олон улсын тэтгэлэг (Yale World Fellow)-т тус тус хамрагдаж  байсан юм. Мөн хатагтай Ц.Оюунгэрэлийг Монгол улсад ардчиллыг бэхжүүлэх, хүний эрх, эрх чөлөөг дэмжих, хууль ёсыг тогтоон барихад оруулсан үнэтэй хувь нэмрийг нь үнэлэн 2003 онд Монголын Ардчиллын Холбооноос “Эрх чөлөөний одон”-гоор шагнасан юм.</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/oyungerel.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
	<speaker>
		<name>Sanchir Tserendorj</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Ms. Sanchir is an artist and expert in Mongolian art and cultural studies. As Director of the Organization for the Study of diaspora Mongols, she initiated the making of documentary episodes about diaspora Mongols, working on research, photography, and the film script.
		
In 2004, Ms. Sanchir directed 30 research and documentary video expeditions to Islamic countries, closed countries in the Middle East about diaspora Mongolian groups. In 2009-2010, Ms. Sanchir was the leader of TASAM-12 documentary series, research and video expedition team.
		
In 2010 Ms. Sanchir was the project leader for Mongols with a Royal History, a project recounting the story of diaspora Mongols who had been posted to secure the conquered land and their distinct ethnic uniqueness, traditions, and clothing which they have preserved, and the tangible cultural heritage Mongols built during the 100 years of their reign in Middle Eastern countries.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Уран бүтээлч Санчир нь Монголын урлаг, соёл судлалын мэргэжилтэн юм. Монголын үндэстний цөөнхийг судлах байгууллагын захирлаар ажилладаг тэрээр Монголын үндэстний цөөнхийн тухай цуврал баримтат кино бүтээхээр санаачилсан бөгөөд одоогоор судалгаа шинжилгээ, гэрэл зураг, зохиол бичих ажлуудыг гүйцэтгэж байна.

Хатагтай Санчир 2004 онд Монголын үндэстний цөөнхийг судлах ажлаар Ойрхи Дорнод дахь хаалттай орнуудаар буюу Исламын орнуудаар явж, 30 судалгаа ба баримтат киноны зураг авалтын багийг ахалж ажилласан туршлагатай. Мөн тэрээр 2009-2010 онд TASAM-12 цуврал баримтат киноны судалгаа, зураг авалтын багийн ахлагчаар ажиллаж байсан. 

2010 онд Хатагтай Санчир эзэлж авсан газар нутгаа хамгаалах үүрэг хүлээн одоогийн Ойрхи Дорнодын орнуудад үлдсэн Монгол үндэстний цөөнх болон Ойрхи Дорнодод хаанчлал тогтоосон 100 жилийн хугацаанд бий болгосон Монголчуудын өвөрмөц соёл, үндэстний онцлог, уламжлал, зан заншил, өмсгөл хувцас зэрэг зүйлсийг дэлгэрэнгүй харуулах төсөл “Дээдийн түүхтэй Монгол”-ийг ахлан ажиллаж байсан юм.</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/sanchir-tserendorj.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>
	<speaker>
		<name>Didi Kalika</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>In 1993 Didi Kalika, an Australian yoga teacher living in UB was moved by the plight of the children living on the streets and founded the Lotus Children's Centre. She started simply by giving food and basic medical care, and soon realized that serious change was necessary to make real impact. With the help of friends, Didi arranged a yard in the ger district of Yarmag 15 km out of UB. The move to Yarmag was necessary to give children space away from their lives on the streets of UB. In 1995, the Lotus Children's Centre was registered as an official Mongolian charity. Towards the end of the 90's, the children Lotus served moved from mainly street kids to abandoned babies. Due to harsh economic conditions, some Mongolian families found it hard to keep their newborn babies. Mongolian authorities asked Lotus to care for babies that were found under stairwells or in rubbish bins, often in the depth of winter. The Lotus Centre started a Kindergarten on the Yarmag property in 1997. It was around this time that their summer camp started, sending kids to the National Park in Terelj for their summer holidays to play and swim.
		
Didi was awarded Mongolian mother of the year award in 2001. She was also made a Paul Harris fellow by the Rotary Club of Canberra Sunshine.

Due to the lack of necessary paperwork for Lotus children to start at government schools, in 2004, Lotus converted an old general goods store in Yarmag into a primary school. The kindergarten was moved into the same building. This was necessary to guarantee that all Lotus children would have an education up to the 5th grade. Around this time the situation of children in Mongolia gradually improved, with less babies coming to the center. The Lotus Centre is now home to up to 150 children at any one time. It carries out many children and family support activities aimed at helping family units endure. The Lotus Centre aims to alleviate the poverty cycle and to ultimately provide basic rights to children.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Улаанбаатар хотод амьдардаг Австралийн ёогийн багш Диди Калика гудамжны хүүхдүүдийн төлөө сэтгэл зовнин, “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвийг үүсгэн байгуулсан. Анхандаа хүүхдүүдийг хоол хүнс, эрүүл мэндийн үйлчилгээгээр хангаж байсан боловч дараа нь бодит үр дүнд хүрэхийн тулд томоохон өөрчлөлт хийх шаардлагатай гэдгийг ойлгосон. Диди найзуудынхаа тусламжтайгаар Улаанбаатараас 15 км-ийн зайд байрлах Яармагийн гэр хороололд нэг ярд газар авч чадсан. Ийнхүү хотоос зайдуу газарлуу нүүх нь хүүхдүүдийг сурч дассан гудамжны амьдралаасаа ангижирахад нь чухал нөлөөтэй байсан юм. 1995 онд “Лотус” хүүхдийн төв Монголын албан ёсны халамжийн байгууллагаар бүртгэгдсэн. 1990-ээд оны сүүлээр “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвд гудамжны хүүхдүүдээс гадна хаягдмал хүүхдүүд ирэх болсон. Учир нь хүнд хэцүү эдийн засгийн нөхцөл байдлаас үүдэн зарим айл өрхүүд шинээр мэндэлсэн хүүхдээ тэжээхэд бэрх үе байсан юм. Тиймээс Монголын засгийн газар “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвийг дүн өвлийн хүйтэнд шатны доор эсвэл хогийн саванд хаягдсан хүүхдүүдийг авч асрах хүсэлтийг тавьсан. “Лотус” хүүхдийн төв 1997 оноос эхлэн Яармагт хүүхдийн цэцэрлэг ажиллуулж эхэлсэн. Тухайн жилдээ хүүхдүүдэд зориулсан зуны зусланг “Тэрэлж” үндэсний соёл амралтын хүрээлэнд бий болгосон. Хүүхдүүд зуны амралтаараа тэнд очиж амардаг байв.

2001 онд Диди “Монгол ээж” цолоор шагнуулсан. Мөн тэрээр Канберра Саншайн (Canberra Sunshine)-ий Ротари клубын Paul Harris fellow шагналаар шагнагдсан. “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвийн хүүхдүүд улсын сургуульд хамрагдахад шаардлагатай бичиг баримтууд дутуу байсан тул 2004 онд Яармаг дахь барааны дэлгүүрийг тусгай бага сургууль болгосон. Тус сургуулийн байранд “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвийн цэцэрлэгийг мөн нүүлгэн оруулсан. Ингэснээр “Лотус” хүүхдийн төвийн хүүхдүүд 5-р анги хүртэлх боловсролыг эзэмших боломжтой болсон юм. Энэ хугацаанд Монгол дахь хүүхдүүдийн нөхцөл байдал аажмаар сайжирсан тул тус төвд ирэх хүүхдүүдийн тоо цөөрч байсан. Одоо “Лотус” хүүхдийн төв нь ойролцоогоор 150 хүүхдүүдийн гэр нь болж байна. Тус төв нь айл өрхүүдэд туслах зорилгоор хүүхдүүд ба гэр бүлийг дэмжихэд чиглэгдсэн олон арга хэмжээнүүдийг авч байна. “Лотус” хүүхдийн төв нь ядуурлыг бууруулах болон хүүхдийн эрхийг хамгаалах зорилготойгоор үйл ажиллагаагаа явуулж байна.</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/didi-kalika.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>
	<speaker>
		<name>Ganhuyag Chuluun Hutagt</name>
		<talkTitle_en></talkTitle_en>
		<talkTitle_mn></talkTitle_mn>
		<description_en>Ganhuyag started his career at the Mongolian Stock Exchange as a floor supervisor in 1991 and moved on to become engaged in the family trading business a year later. He joined the Central Bank’s Supervision Division after graduating from the Budapest University of Economic Sciences in 1997. He was hired by UNDP’s MicroStart Pilot Project in 1998, initially as a Finance Manager and then Operations Manager before becoming the Executive Director of Mongolia’s first non-bank financial company X.A.C. (Golden Fund for Development). In 1999. X.A.C. subsequently merged with USAID funded Goviin Ekhlel (GobiStart) LLC to form XacBank. He held the position of the CEO of XacBank from the founding until 2009.
		
In June 2007, he was elected to the Board of the Microfinance Center for Central Asia and Eastern Europe and the New Independent States (MFC). He has been serving as the Honorary Consul of the Republic of Hungary in Mongolia since 2006 and as the President of the Mongolian Students’ Union since January 2010. The World Economic Forum named him a Young Global Leader in 2009.

Before being appointed as the Vice Minister of Finance of Mongolia in December 2010, he worked as the CEO of TenGer Financial Group and the economic policy advisor to the Prime Minister of Mongolia.</description_en>
		<description_mn>Чулууны Ганхуяг 1991 онд Монголын Хөрөнгийн Биржид үйл ажиллагааны танхимын ахлахаас ажлын гараагаа эхэлсэн бөгөөд жилийн дараа гэр бүлийнхээ худалдааны бизнест оролцох болсон юм. Тэрээр 1997 онд Будадештийн Эдийн Засгийн Их Сургуулийг төгсч ирснийхээ дараа Монгол Банкны Хяналтын Хэлтэст орж ажилласан. Тэрээр 1998 онд НҮБ-ын Хөгжлийн Сангийн MicroStart туршилтын төсөлд санхүүгийн менежерээр орж ажилласан бөгөөд дараа нь үйл ажиллагааны менежерийн үүрэг гүйцэтгэх болсон. Хожим нь тэрээр Монголын анхны банк бус санхүүгийн байгууллага X.A.C. (Хөгжлийн Алтан Сан)-ийн гүйцэтгэх захирлаар ажиллах болсон. 1999 онд X.A.C. НҮБ-ын Хөгжлийн Сангаас хөрөнгө оруулалт хийсэн Говийн Эхлэл ХХК-тай нэгдэн ХасБанкийг үүсгэн бий болгосон. Чулууны Ганхуяг ХасБанкийг үүсгэн байгуулснаасаа хойш 2009 он хүртэл CEO-аар ажилласан юм.

Тэрээр 2007 оны 6-р сард Төв Ази, Зүүн Европын Бичил Санхүүгийн Төв болон Шинэ Тусгаар Улс буюу New Independent States (MFC)-ын удирдах зөвлөлөөр сонгогдсон. Мөн тэрээр 2006 оноос хойш Бүгд Найрамдах Унгар Улсын Хүндэт Консулаар ажиллаж байгаа бөгөөд 2010 оны 1-р сараас Монголын Оюутны Холбооны Ерөнхийлөгчөөр ажиллаж байна. 2009 онд Дэлхийн Эдийн Засгийн Форумаас Чулууны Ганхуягийг Дэлхийн Залуу Удирдагчаар нэрлэсэн юм.

Чулууны Ганхуяг 2010 оны 12-р сард Монгол улсын Сангийн дэд сайдаар томилогдохоосоо өмнө ТэнГэр санхүүгийн нэгдлийн СЕО болон Монгол Улсын Ерөнхий Сайдын эдийн засгийн бодлогын зөвлөхөөр ажиллаж байсан юм.</description_mn>
		<thumbnail>http://arssollertia.com/tedxub/ganhuyag-chuluun.jpg</thumbnail>
	</speaker>	
</speakers>